<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Datasets | HBM Hackathon]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/categories/datasets/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-17T13:21:43-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OHBM Organizing Committee]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[hbm.hackathon@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NeuroDebian: The ultimate neuroscience software platform]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/06/11/neurodebian-the-ultimate-neuroscience-software-platform/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T18:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/06/11/neurodebian-the-ultimate-neuroscience-software-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/NeuroDebian.png" title="&#34;NeuroDebian&#34;" alt="&#34;NeuroDebian&#34;"></p>

<p><a href="http://neuro.debian.net">NeuroDebian</a> is a turnkey software platform for nearly all aspects of the neuroscientific research process.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>NeuroDebian provides a large collection of popular neuroscience research software for the <a href="http://www.debian.org">Debian</a> operating system as well as <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu</a> and other derivatives.  Moreover it provides some popular datasets and atlases within the same convenient package management system.</p>

<h3>Software</h3>

<p>Popular neuroscience-oriented packages include <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/afni.html">AFNI</a>, <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/fsl.html">FSL</a>, <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/python-mvpa2.html">PyMVPA</a> and <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs.html">many others</a>. In addition popular projects for generic (e.g. <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/python-pandas.html">pandas</a>, <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/xppaut.html">xppaut</a>) and distributed (e.g., <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/coop-computing-tools.html">coop-computing-tools</a>, <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/condor.html">condor</a>) computation needs are included.  The <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs.html">entire list</a> is too long to cite here.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<ul>
<li>Atlases provided by software such as <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/fsl.html">FSL</a> and <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/afni.html">AFNI</a></li>
<li><a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/neurosynth-dataset.html">NeuroSynth dataset</a> and <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/fsl-neurosynth-atlas.html">its FSL atlas</a></li>
<li><a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/haxby2001-faceobject.html">Haxby 2001</a> dataset</li>
<li><a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkgs/python-mvpa2-tutorialdata.html">PyMVPA tutorial</a> (including data and IPython notebook)</li>
<li>See <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/pkglists/toc_pkgs_for_release_data.html">our website</a> for the exhaustive list</li>
</ul>


<h3>Installation</h3>

<p>Majority of software packaged by NeuroDebian team is integrated are already available on any stock <a href="http://www.debian.org">Debian</a> or <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com">Ubuntu</a> system.  In addition we maintain a dedicated <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/#get-neurodebian">NeuroDebian repository</a> which you could add to APT sources on your stock Debian/Ubuntu installation to obtain most recent versions and software we maintain AND data packages which are absent from official Debian and Ubuntu archives.</p>

<h4>Personal virtualization</h4>

<p>Pre-crafted <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/vm.html">NeuroDebian virtual appliance</a> allows to start using NeuroDebian and thousands of available software packages on any operating system in matter of minutes.</p>

<h4>Cloud</h4>

<p>NeuroDebian provides software for the NITRC-CE environment available for the hackathon participants.</p>

<h3>Support</h3>

<p><a href="mailto:team@neuro.debian.net">Email us directly</a> with any "private" communication. Otherwise please use our <a href="http://lists.alioth.debian.org/mailman/listinfo/neurodebian-users">public mailing list</a> with any support questions.</p>

<p>You are welcome also to join #neurodebian IRC room on OFTC network if you have quick questions or want to join a live discussion.</p>

<p>Please visit our <a href="http://neuro.debian.net/about.html#chap-contacts">support</a> page for additional channels.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>If you are not using NeuroDebian <em>already</em> - you must try it now!</p>

<!-- some packages worth mentioning -->



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NIF: an inventory of Web-based neuroscience resources]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/29/nif-an-inventory-of-web-based-neuroscience-resources/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T14:03:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/29/nif-an-inventory-of-web-based-neuroscience-resources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.neuinfo.org/images/nif-logo.png" width="75" title="&#34;NIF&#34;" alt="&#34;NIF&#34;"></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.neuinfo.org">Neuroscience Information Framework</a>: neuroscience data, materials, and tools  via any computer connected to the Internet.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>Background</h4>

<p>Currently NIF Offers:</p>

<ol>
<li>A <a href="http://www.neuinfo.org/nif/nifgwt.html">search</a> portal for researchers looking for neuroscience information, tools, data or materials</li>
<li>Access to content normally not indexed by search engines (i.e, the "hidden web")</li>
<li><a href="http://neuinfo.org/nif_components/disco/interoperation.shtm">Tools</a> for promoting interoperability among databases</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.neuinfo.org/vocabularies/index.shtm">NIFSTD ontology</a> covering the major domains of neuroscience (e.g., brain anatomy, cells, organisms, diseases, techniques)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.neuinfo.org/developers/index.shtm">Developer resources</a> for accessing the NIF vocabulary and NIF tools, such as <a href="http://neuinfo.org/developers/nif_web_services.shtm">web services</a> and including a <a href="http://neuinfo.org/tutorials/developers_tool/federated_data.shtm">tutorial</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Some particular data sets which can be offered are Brain Connectivity Data (50316 records), Brain Activation Foci (5,145), Diseases (1,521), Microarray (642,995):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.neuinfo.org/mynif/search.php?q=connectivity&amp;first=true&amp;cf=Connectivity">Integrated Nervous System Connectivity View</a> is an aggregated dataset of connectivity statements from BAMS, CoCoMac, BrainMaps, Connectome Wiki, the Hippocampal-Parahippocampal Table of Temporal-Lobe.com and the Avian Brain Circuitry Database.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.neuinfo.org/mynif/search.php?q=connectivity&amp;first=true&amp;cf=Disease&amp;t=indexable&amp;nif=nlx_86401-1">Integrated Disease View</a> is a virtual database currently indexing authoritative information on disease and treatment options from: NINDS Disorder List and PubMed Health.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.neuinfo.org/mynif/search.php?q=connectivity&amp;first=true&amp;cf=Brain%20Activation%20Foci">Activation Foci</a> data provides functional activation foci data from published neuroimaging studies.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Example Responses to Challenges</h4>

<p><strong>Challenge 1:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Use NIF neuron registry to identify cell systems in various neurodegenerative diseases and map it to ABA data.</li>
<li>For different diseases, use NeuronRegistry-NeuroLex to infer from genes what specific cell populations differently effect neuron types. Also, we'd like to link those cell systems in Neurodegenerative diseases to neurotransmitter data in NeuronRegistry.</li>
<li>For example, in Alzheimer we want to examine ABA genes and how differently they affect different group of neurons found in NeuronRegistry. Infer what cell populations impacted in various brain regions.</li>
<li>ABA has mapped neurotransmitter related genes, thus one challenge is: <strong>Are there specific neurotransmitter systems affected in mental disorders and do they map to any known cell type?</strong></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Challenge 2:</strong></p>

<p>Use NIF cell data as a bridge between resting data and projections of know cell types in various brain regions (ABA). Use Neurolex (NIF) and tractography (NIF) data we can estimate what type of cells where can cell body are and where axon projected.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Explore and get public fMRI datasets from COINS Data Exchange]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/14/explore-and-get-public-fmri-datasets-from-coins-data-exchange/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-14T13:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/14/explore-and-get-public-fmri-datasets-from-coins-data-exchange</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://d1yzvr466z4u1c.cloudfront.net/image02.jpg" alt="COINS Banner" style="width:100%;" /></p>

<p>COINS manages fMRI, MEG and phenotypic data for over 400 studies across six research institutions.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>An ever-increasing subset of this data is being made publicly available on the COINS Data Exchange. Currently, the research community can explore and request raw MRI, fMRI and phenotypic data from several independent studies.</p>

<h3>Tutorial:</h3>

<p>A simple video-tutorial for querying can be seen on the COINS Data Exchange site, or on <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YjMbCq5NBuc">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/YjMbCq5NBuc "></iframe></div></p>

<h3>Exploration:</h3>

<p>Creating a COINS account is easy. Just go to <a href="http://coins.mrn.org/dx">http://coins.mrn.org/dx</a>, enter your email address, make up a password and click ‘Get Account’.  That account is needed to let you know when your data are available for download, and to track any data agreements necessary for specific datasets. It is recommended that you do this prior to the Hackathon, just to explore the Data Exchange before needing to use it.</p>

<p>Once your account has been created, you can browse data in the Data Exchange. A unique filtering tool allows you to construct complex queries by combining data filters into logical groups and sub-groups. The goal of the exploration should be to target the exact data that is useful to you before you request and download it. This will save bandwidth and computing time on the COINS servers. Additionally, a well-targeted request will save you time by decreasing the need to post-filter data after download.</p>

<h3>Approval:</h3>

<p>Once you have found your ideal data, you can request that data by clicking the ‘Request’ button at the top-right. Though all data in the COINS data exchange is fully anonymized and defaced, some studies will need to explicitly approve your request. For this reason, you can provide information about your intentions for the data that you are requesting. Other studies (ABIDE, for example) have pre-approved their data for instant download. Each data-source is approved independently, so you can start downloading data as it is approved.</p>

<h3>Delivery:</h3>

<p>Approved data is packaged into ‘Data Capsules’ on the COINS servers. You will receive an email when your Data Capsule is ready, and you can then begin your download(s).</p>

<h3>Using COINS Data Exchange to meet your OHBM Hackathon objectives:</h3>

<p>At present, the COINS Data Exchange is only accessible through the browser interface at <a href="http://coins.mrn.org/dx">http://coins.mrn.org/dx</a>. However, once your data has been approved and packaged for download, you can download each data capsule directly to another web-server or cloud-based storage device from the command line or a script.</p>

<p>After choosing which capsule to download, a dialog will appear with a temporary URL that can be used to request the capsule directly. The link will expire as soon as the download button is clicked, or after five minutes, so please do not click on the data until you are ready to download it..
<img src="http://d1yzvr466z4u1c.cloudfront.net/image01.png" alt="COINS Banner" style="max-width:100%;" /></p>

<p>Downloaded imaging data may consist of DICOM or NIfTI files, and will be organized in the following file-hierarchy:</p>

<p><img src="http://d1yzvr466z4u1c.cloudfront.net/image00.png" alt="COINS Banner" style="max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>Downloaded phenotypic (assessment) data will be contained in CSV files: one per instrument (questionnaire form).</p>

<h3>Currently Available Datasets:</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>ABIDE:</strong> from <a href="http://fcon_1000.projects.nitrc.org/indi/abide/">http://fcon_1000.projects.nitrc.org/indi/abide/</a>: In response, the Autism Brain Imaging Data Exchange (ABIDE) hereby provides previously collected resting state functional magnetic resonance imaging (R-fMRI) datasets from 539 individuals with ASD and 573 typical controls for the purpose of data sharing in the broader scientific community. Various cognitive and clinical assessments are also available. These data are pre-approved for sharing.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Discovery Sci:</strong> <a href="http://fcon_1000.projects.nitrc.org/indi/pro/nki.html">http://fcon_1000.projects.nitrc.org/indi/pro/nki.html</a>: The NKI/Rockland Sample is intended to be a phenotypically rich neuroimaging sample, consisting of data obtained from individuals between the ages of 4 and 85 year-old. All individuals to be included in the sample undergo semi-structured diagnostic psychiatric interviews, and complete a battery of psychiatric, cognitive and behavioral assessments in order to provide comprehensive phenotypic information for the purpose of exploring brain/behavior relationships. Data from the NKI/Rockland sample will be given away prospectively, during the course of acquisition (randomized 2-8 week lag). These data require a data sharing agreement which can be quickly approved.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>MCIC:</strong> The MIND Clinical Imaging Consortium is composed of The Mental Illness and Neuroscience Discovery Institute, now the Mind Research Network (MRN, <a href="http://mrn.org">http://mrn.org</a>), comprised of investigators at the University of New Mexico, the University of Minnesota, Massachusetts General Hospital, and the University of Iowa (data from this site not available). The MCIC consortium conducted a cross-sectional study to identify quantitative neuroimaging biomarkers of schizophrenia. Expertly collected, well-curated data sets consisting of comprehensive clinical characterization and raw structural, functional and diffusion-weighted DICOM images in schizophrenia patients (n=162) and sex and age-matched controls (n=169) are now accessible to the scientific community. These data also require a data sharing agreement which can be quickly approved.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Contact:</h3>

<p>The COINS developers are excited to support the OHBM Hackathon participants. Any requests, questions or feedback can be directed to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;&#x3a;&#x6e;&#105;&#x40;&#x6d;&#x72;&#x6e;&#x2e;&#111;&#x72;&#103;">&#x6e;&#105;&#64;&#x6d;&#114;&#110;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NITRC-CE: A computational resource for the HBM Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/13/nitrc-ce-a-cloud-based-computational-resource-for-the-hbm-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T12:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/13/nitrc-ce-a-cloud-based-computational-resource-for-the-hbm-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/NITRC-CE.png" title="&#34;NITRC-CE&#34;" alt="&#34;NITRC-CE&#34;"></p>

<p>NITRC-CE is an on-demand, cloud based computational virtual machine pre-installed with popular NITRC neuroimaging tools.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In January of 2013, the Neuroimaging Informatics Tools and Resources Clearinghouse (<a href="http://www.nitrc.org">NITRC</a>) released it's Computational Environment (NITRC-CE), an on-demand, cloud based computational virtual machine pre-installed with popular NITRC neuroimaging tools built using NeuroDebian.</p>

<h3>Purpose</h3>

<p>The NITRC-CE is designed to be a low-barrier entry point to accessing the power of the cloud-based computing environment by providing a fully configured, ready to go EC2 instance within just a few clicks of the mouse.</p>

<h3>Access</h3>

<p>NITRC-CE is available via the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00AW0MBLO">Amazon Marketplace</a>. In addition,  you can also access a 'public AMI' to conduct your analyses on the Amazon EC2 platform.  The NITRC-CE is scalable and extensible, and preconfigured with many <a href="http://www.nitrc.org/plugins/mwiki/index.php/nitrc:User_Guide_-_NITRC-CE_Installed_Packages">software packages</a>. Additional software supported under Ubuntu 12.04 LTE can be added by the user.</p>

<h3>Data</h3>

<p>Each NITRC-CE instance has remote access, so that users own data can be copied to and from using 'scp' and 'sftp'. In addition, The NITRC-CE desktop is one-click away from the NITRC Image Repository (NITRC-IR), home of data for the 1000 Functional Connectomes, ADHD-200, ABIDE and other datasets. In addition, the NDAR download manager is available to assist in access to your NDAR datasets. Additional access points to other Hackathon data will be added in the near future.</p>

<h3>Support</h3>

<p>The staff of NITRC are available to assist users with issues (<strong><a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#110;&#105;&#x74;&#x72;&#x69;&#x63;&#105;&#110;&#x66;&#x6f;&#64;&#x6e;&#105;&#116;&#x72;&#x63;&#46;&#111;&#x72;&#103;">&#x6e;&#105;&#116;&#114;&#105;&#99;&#105;&#110;&#102;&#111;&#64;&#110;&#x69;&#x74;&#x72;&#99;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#x72;&#103;</a></strong>), and a comprehensive <a href="http://www.nitrc.org/plugins/mwiki/index.php/nitrc:User_Guide_-_NITRC_Computational_Environment">Users Guide</a> and discussion forum dedicated to <a href="http://www.nitrc.org/forum/forum.php?thread_id=3897&amp;forum_id=3663">HBM Hackathon support</a>.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Best of luck in your participation in the HBM Hackathon. We hope the NITRC-CE will be a valuable resource to you.  Feel free to contact us with any questions, problems or suggestions for enhanced support of this endeavor.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Human Connectome Project Q1 Release: Now Cloud Accessible]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/03/human-connectome-project-q1-release-now-cloud-accessible/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-03T13:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohbm-seattle.github.io/blog/2013/05/03/human-connectome-project-q1-release-now-cloud-accessible</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.humanconnectome.org/img/header-bg.png" title="&#34;Human Connectom Project&#34;" alt="&#34;Human Connectom Project&#34;"></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/">first full quarterly HCP Data release</a> is now Cloud accessible for participants who have <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/index.html">registered</a> and agreed to the <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/open-access.html">Open Access Data Use Terms</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>HBM Hackathon participants will have the opportunity for high speed access to the first full quarterly HCP Data release via Amazon Web Services. All data available from the HCP Connectome-in-a-Box can now be downloaded directly from S3, Amazon’s Simple Storage Service.</p>

<h4>This post is organized into three sections:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Description of the HCP Q1 Release</li>
<li>Getting Authorized to Access the HCP Data</li>
<li>Accessing HCP Data on AWS</li>
</ol>


<h3>Description of the HCP Q1 Release</h3>

<p>The Q1 data release consists of multimodal MRI data collected from 68 healthy young adults who were scanned in the fall of 2012. These include all 12 subjects from our Initial Data Release. All 3T MRI scan data is included: Structural, Functional (resting state and task) and Diffusion. Behavioral data collected on all subjects is also included, with the exception of sensitive restricted-access data. Please see the <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/documentation/Q1/">Full Release Documentation</a> for further details.</p>

<h3>Getting Authorized to Access the HCP Data</h3>

<p>There are a few steps you will need to take to get authorization to access the HCP data hosted on AWS.</p>

<h4>You need to:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Complete the <strong><a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/index.html">HCP Registration</a></strong> and agree to the <strong><a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/open-access.html">HCP Open Access Data Use Terms</a></strong></li>
<li>Complete the <strong><a href="http://www.humanbrainmapping.org/hackathon">HBM Hackathon Registration</a></strong></li>
<li>Create an <strong><a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon Web Services Account</a></strong></li>
<li>Email <strong><a href="&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x68;&#98;&#x6d;&#x2e;&#x68;&#x61;&#x63;&#107;&#x61;&#x74;&#104;&#x6f;&#110;&#x40;&#x67;&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#104;&#98;&#109;&#x2e;&#x68;&#x61;&#99;&#x6b;&#97;&#116;&#104;&#x6f;&#110;&#x40;&#103;&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a></strong> with your HCP and AWS email address(es)</li>
</ol>


<h4>A foreword from David van Essen:</h4>

<blockquote><p><strong>For distribution to all investigators interested in using HCP Connectome-in-a-Box data.</strong><br/>
</br>
<strong>IMPORTANT NOTICE to investigators wanting to use HCP datasets available on Connectome-in-a-Box hard drives.</strong><br/>
</br>
HCP’s Connectome-in-a-Box provides imaging data from the Open Access dataset. Before using any of these data for research, you and all other investigators using the data are required to <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/index.html">register</a> and agree to the <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/open-access.html">Open Access Data Use Terms</a>. <strong>This includes agreeing to comply with institutional rules and regulations</strong>.  This may mean that you need your research to be approved or declared exempt by a committee that oversees research on human subjects (e.g., your IRB or Ethics Committee).  The released HCP data are not considered de-identified, insofar as certain combinations of HCP Restricted Data (available through a separate process) might allow identification of individuals.  Different committees operate under different national, state and local laws and may interpret regulations differently, so it is important to ask about this. If needed and upon request, the HCP will provide a certificate stating that you have accepted the HCP Open Access Data Use Terms.<br/>
</br>
Sincerely,<br/>
David C. Van Essen (PI), for the WU-Minn HCP Consortium<br/>
May 1, 2013</p></blockquote>

<h3>Accessing HCP Data on AWS</h3>

<p>Amazon Web Services is hosting the HCP Q1 Data Release as part of its Public Data Sets on AWS program, which will enable HBM Hackathon participants to get rapid access to the HCP data. Since the data is hosted on S3 in an uncompressed format, participants can download data in parallel using tools like <a href="https://github.com/pcorliss/s3cmd-modification">s3cmd-modification</a>.</p>

<p>You can use tools like <a href="https://github.com/pcorliss/s3cmd-modification">s3cmd</a> to list the contents of a directory on S3, get individual files or sync full directories. You will also be able to download directly to your personal/work computer or to a machine on the EC2 Cloud like the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00AW0MBLO">NITRC Computational Environment</a>.</p>

<h4>Getting Credentials</h4>

<p>Ready to start downloading? Make sure you've completed the <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/index.html">HCP registration</a> and <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">created an account with AWS</a>.</p>

<p>Next, send an email to <strong><a href="&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#x68;&#x62;&#109;&#46;&#x68;&#x61;&#x63;&#x6b;&#97;&#116;&#x68;&#111;&#x6e;&#x40;&#x67;&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;">&#104;&#98;&#x6d;&#46;&#x68;&#x61;&#x63;&#x6b;&#97;&#x74;&#x68;&#111;&#110;&#64;&#103;&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;</a></strong> with your HCP and AWS email address(es).</p>

<p>We will use your HCP and AWS email address(es) to:</p>

<ol>
<li>verify that you have agreed to the <a href="http://www.humanconnectome.org/data/data-use-terms/open-access.html">Open Access Data Use Agreement</a></li>
<li>grant you access to the HCP data on AWS.</li>
</ol>


<p>Once verified, you will receive an email confirming that you have access to the HCP data on AWS.</p>

<h4>Configuring your system</h4>

<p>To access the data you'll want to install <a href="https://github.com/pcorliss/s3cmd-modification">s3cmd-modification</a>, which will enable you to explore the <a href="http://humanconnectome.org/documentation/data-release/Q1_Release_Appendix_III.pdf">HCP Data Directory</a> on Amazon and will allow rapid parallel downloading (<a href="https://github.com/pcorliss/s3cmd-modification/blob/master/INSTALL">s3cmd-modification install instructions</a>).</p>

<p>After you install s3cmd, you need to configure it with your AWS public and secret keys, located in <a href="https://portal.aws.amazon.com/gp/aws/securityCredentials">AWS Security Credentials</a>.</p>

<pre><code>:~ s3cmd --configure
Enter new values or accept defaults in brackets with Enter.
Refer to user manual for detailed description of all options.

Access key and Secret key are your identifiers for Amazon S3
Access Key []: &lt;your-access-key&gt;
Secret Key []: &lt;your-secret-key&gt;
... 
</code></pre>

<p>Take s3cmd out for a test drive...</p>

<p>List subject directories:</p>

<pre><code>:~ s3cmd ls s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/

DIR   s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/100307/
DIR   s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/103515/
DIR   s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/111312/
...
DIR   s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/937160/
2013-04-17 06:57         0   s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/
</code></pre>

<p>Get a directory in parallel:</p>

<pre><code>:~ s3cmd --parallel --workers=16 get --recursive s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/100307/T1w T1w

File s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/100307/T1w/BiasField_acpc_dc.nii.gz started [2 of 52]
File s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/100307/T1w/Native/100307.L.MyelinMap.native.func.gii started [3 of 52]
...
File s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/100307/T1w/T2w_acpc_dc_restore.nii.gz saved as 'T1w/T1w/T2w_acpc_dc_restore.nii.gz' (67855816 bytes in 143.3 seconds, 462.31 kB/s)
File s3://hcp.aws.amazon.com/q1/100307/T1w/BiasField_acpc_dc.nii.gz saved as 'T1w/T1w/BiasField_acpc_dc.nii.gz' (65076318 bytes in 180.3 seconds, 352.50 kB/s)
</code></pre>

<p>If everything checks out, you are ready to get hacking!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
